Guide to the Howard Gillette Metropolitan Washington Region Urban History subject files, 1873-1995 MS2060
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Howard Gillette Metropolitan Washington Region Urban History subject files
1873-1995
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Gillette, Howard, Jr.,, 1942 -
MS2060
7.5 Linear Feet
Collection includes materials on the history of the greater Washington, D.C. metropolitan area. The collection documents the history of DC communities, focusing on community structure, organizations, politics, events, transportation and difficulties, such as crime and includes paper articles, brochures, pamphlets and letters.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
[required]
Historical or Biographical Note
The collection is focused on the history of the greater Washington, D.C. metropolitan area. More specifically it documents the history of DC communities, focusing on community structure, organizations, politics, events, transportation and difficulties, such as crime. Upon receipt the collection was already divided into labeled folders. In processing this collection I abided by this organization and merely sorted these folders into the broader series of: Geographic Locations, Organizations, Politics and Individuals.
The collection is housed in 15 boxes and consists mostly of newspaper articles, brochures, pamphlets and letters. The dates of the documents range from the late 1800s until the late 1990s.
The donation was made in January 1995, by Howard Gillette.
Collection Scope and Content
The collection includes materials on the history of the greater Washington, D.C. metropolitan area. The collection documents the history of DC communities, focusing on community structure, organizations, politics, events, transportation and difficulties, such as crime and includes paper articles, brochures, pamphlets and letters.
The collection was received already divided into labeled folders, therefore the organization remains according to provenance, but has been divided into the following four series: Geographic Locations; Organizations; Politics; and Individual.
The collection is housed in 15 boxes and ranges in date from the late 1800s until the late 1990s.
Collection Organization
Organized into four series: Geographic locations, Organizations, Politics, and Individual.
Washington (D.C.) -- History; Washington (D.C.); Community development; Politics and government; Rolark, Calvin; Kelly, Sharon Pratt; Historical Society of Washington, D.C.; Barry, Marion; Shepherd, Alexander Robey
- Geographic Locations, 1873-1995; MS2060 Series 1; 3.75 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes geopraphic locations of the greater Washington area from 1873-1995.
  - Alexandria, 1978-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alexandria -- metro, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alleys, 1890-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anacostia, 1979-1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anacostia Clips, 1979-1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Anacostia Museum, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Anacostia River, 1987-1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Apartment Buildings, 1977-1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Arlington, 1977-1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Baltimore/Washington Corridor, 1987-1993 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Barney Neighborhood House, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Barry Farm, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bethesda, 1983-1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Boundary Stones, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Burleith, 1972-1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Capitol Hill, 1976-1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Centre Market, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Chinatown, 1972-1994 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Cleveland Park, 1973-1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - C&O Canal, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Deanwood, 1988-1993 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Downtown, 1977-1992 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Downtown Exhibit, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Dulles Corridor, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - DuPont Circle, 1982-1993 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Ellen Wilson -- Housing, 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Engine 4 Block Firehouse, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Fairfax, 1976-1992 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Fairfax -- County History, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Fairfax County Economic Development Authority, 1985-1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - FDR Memorial, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Federal Triangle, 1971-1993 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Foggy Bottom, 1987-1995 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Forrest Marbury Court, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Ft. Lincoln, 1969-1981 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - George Mason University, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Georgetown, 1966-1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Georgetown -- Grace Episcopal Church, 1974-1981 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Georgetown Market, 1969-1985 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Georgetown Waterfront, 1968-1986 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - H Street, 1981-1994 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Henderson Castle, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Highland Beach, 1985-1993 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Howard County, 1986-1991 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Ivy City, 1977-1993 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Kalorama, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Kenesaw, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Lafayette Square, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Lansburgh, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Le Droit Park, 1877-1996 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Logan Circle, 1973-1994 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Loudoun County, 1983-1991 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Marshall Heights, 1948-1997 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Montgomery County, 1957-1992 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Mount Pleasant, 1911-1991 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Mount Pleasant -- Land and Community Survey, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Mount Pleasant Newsletters, 1977-1993 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Mount Pleasant: Suburban Village to Urban Neighborhood --report, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Mt. Zion United Methodist Church, 1984-1994 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Murder Bay, 1873-1888 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Museum of the Building Arts, 1977-1981 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - National Building Museum, 1983-1986 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Navy Yard, 1980-1997 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Patent Office Building, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Pennsylvania Avenue, 1976-1992 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Port America, 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Post Office, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Potomac River Basin -- In the Anacostia Watershed, 1988-1994 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Potomac River Basin -- Potomac Basin Reporter, 1986-1994 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Prince George County, 1990-1997 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Prince George County, 1967-1989 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Prince William County, 1984-1988 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Red Lion Row, 1979-1983 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Rockville, 1978-1993 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Rhodes Tavern, 1980-1984 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Seventh Street, 1979-1991 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Silver Spring, 1979-1991 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Southwest -- general, 1983-1991 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Southwest -- newspaper articles, 1952-1995 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Southwest -- Redevelopment/Urban Renewal, 1951-1963 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Southwest -- Redevelopment/Urban Renewal, 1970-1993 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Southwest -- Oral History Project, 1971-1974 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Studio School, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Organizations, 1939-1995; MS2060 Series 2; 3.25 Linear feet
  This series includes information about many organizations related to the Washington, DC area from 1939-95.
  - Adams Morgan Community Development Corporation, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Associates for Renewal in Education, 1975-1984 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Barbers, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Bicentennial, 1983-1991 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Board of Trade, 1939-1991 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Board of Trade -- undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Business: African-American, 1983-1984 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Business: High Tech, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Business: McGuire Family, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Business: Marriott, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - City Museum Project, 1977-1980 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Cleveland Park -- Historical Preservation, 1984-1991 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - DC Humanities, 1981-1994 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - DC Planning, 1960-1989 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - DC Public Schools, 1992-1993 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Death Penalty, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Don't Tear it Down, 1976-1984 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Drug War, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Ethnic Communities, 1972-1995 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Federal City Council, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Federal Employment, 1969-1982 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Federation of Civic Associations, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Gospel Group, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Greyhound Station, 1987-1988 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Historic Landmarks Legislation, 1978-1983 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Historic Preservation, 1978-1990 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Historic Sites and Places, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Historical Society of Washington DC, 1982-1986 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Historical Society of Washington DC, 1987-1994 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Historical Society -- Newsletters, 1974-1983 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Historical Society -- Newsletters, 1984-1995 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Homeless, 1987-1989 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Homelessness -- newspaper articles, 1988-1989 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Homelessness -- DC Initiatives, 1990-1997 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Housing/House Calls, 1975-1996 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Howard Theatre, 1977-1995 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Invitations, 1991-1993 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Jewish life, 1985-1994 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Jubilee Housing, undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Kalorama -- Historic district, 1984-1990 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - L'Enfant Trust, 1982-1986 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Markets, 1913-1996 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Mental Health, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Mt. Pleasant -- Historic District, 1977-1986 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - MUSCLE -- Housing Organizations, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Neal Writers' Conference, 1984-1985 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Poetry, 1985-1997 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Prostitution, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Redevelopment Land Agency, 1980-1986 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Street Vendors, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Suburbs: African-American Communities, 1971-1993 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Suburban Traffic Problems, 1984-1992 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Teen-Age Pregnancy, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Theatres, 1977-1993 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Transportation -- Metro, 1969-1986 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Transportation -- Metro: newspaper articles, 1977-1991 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - St. Elizabeth, 1985-1991 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - St Stephens Church, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Techworld, 1985-1986 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Tenleytown, 1974-1989 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Thomas Jefferson High School, 1984-1986 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Tivoli Theatre, 1981-1993 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Warner Theatre, 1985-1989 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    General note
    Selected items from this folder are described below. Please note that this is not a comprehensive list of materials within this folder.
    - Testimony presented to the Preservation Review Board of Washington, D.C.--History of The Warner Theater: 1924-1985, 1985 July 31; Item 1
  - Washington Cathedral, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Washington Center for Metropolitan Studies, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Washington Grove, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Washington STAR, undated (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Wesley Heights, 1988-1989 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - West End, 1972-1987 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Whitelaw Hotel, 1992 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Willard Hotel, 1986 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Wisconsin Avenue, 1986-1988 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Wisconsin Avenue, 1986-1988 (Box 14, Folder 17)
- Politics, 1986-1993; MS2060 Series 3; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series includes information about political campaigns and elections from 1986-93.
  - 1986 Election, undated (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - 1989 --1990 Campaign, undated (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - 1992 Politics, undated (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - 1993 Special Election, undated (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Flyers, 1988-1990 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Flyers, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Flyers, 1996 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Ward 6 Special Election -- Political Flyers, 1997 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - DC Bottle Bill, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Home Rule Act, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Individuals, 1915-1994; MS2060 Series 4; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series includes information on notable Washingtonians, from 1915-94. The majority of information dates from 1972-94.
  - Barry, Marrion, 1972-1990 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Brown, Sayles -- Mayor of Washington, 1915 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Dudley, Tilford and Martha, 1985-1990 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Duncan, John, 1994 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Kelly, Sharon Pratt, 1990-1994 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Press, William, undated (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Regardie, William A, undated (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Rolark, Calvin, 1988-1994 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Scurlock, undated (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Shepard, Alexander Robey, 1875-1994 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Wilson, John, undated (Box 15, Folder 17)